In this episode, we're going to go live on stage to one-on-one session that I did in Dubai at
token 2049 with none other than Jeremy Allaire, the CEO of Circle. In this episode, we discuss
a broad range of topics from really what's happening with Circle and USDC to the broader
stable coin ecosystem and really we also cover some of the challenges to the problems we are seeing
and the crypto to fiat rails in the ecosystem today to some of the issues regarding regulatory
uncertainty. So a very exciting episode and hope you like this live session that we did in Dubai
last month. Enjoy the episode. Guys, good morning. Welcome to number two of token 2049. I'm going
to have a lot of fun today. Over the next couple of minutes, we're going to talk about the entire
stable coin universe. What's happening? Not only with the USDC and Circle, but really cross
the ecosystem. So a lot of exciting topics to cover which you all today. Of course, this is
possible because I'm joined by the co-founder, Chairman and CEO of Circle Jeremy Allaire.
Jeremy, great to have you with us. Thanks. It'll be a fun fact about Jeremy. Many of you know him
as the CEO of Circle, but he's also has a hidden talent which is, he's an avid beatboxer.
So here we go. Everybody in crypto has a special talent itself and we find out about
Jeremy, great to have you with us. Thank you. Before we start a conversation,
maybe can you give us an update or where things are right now with Circle, but especially with
USDC. I just saw you guys cross the 30 billion mark, but maybe give us a bit of snapshot where
things are. Sure. Yeah, I think a lot of different things. I mean, first is USDC has been growing a
lot over the past quarter or two and growing in terms of absolute market share. But I think that
some of the biggest things are we've just been continually improving the fundamental infrastructure
of this. I think one of the advantages that we have and have had historically is that we've
always issued USDC under regulatory framework. And we're now seeing essentially stablecoin
rules coming into place all around the world. And alongside that, that's enabling us to really
expand the market infrastructure that supports USDC. So we've brought online essentially local
banking infrastructure in Singapore, in Hong Kong, in the EU. We're in the process of rolling it out
natively in Brazil and Mexico, Japan, ultimately in the region here and other places. And the key
thing for us is we want to make sure that at a wholesale level that it's very, very easy to
create and redeem USDC as quickly as possible, as captively, efficiently as possible. So we've
been building out that kind of global banking infrastructure working with dozens of banks who
are trying to support the growth of this ecosystem. The other is just advancing the technology of
the protocol itself. So we think about what we do is operating a stablecoin network. And that
network includes the protocols. Those protocols now exist on 16 blockchain networks. We're continually
improving those protocols to make them more efficient, to add new features. We launched a
cross-chain transfer protocol, which enables for teleporting USDC safely across these different
ecosystems, which is really significant. And so we're making that infrastructure faster and easier to
use. And then working with developers in hundreds of countries now who are building on top of those
protocols and building applications, utilities and other things to help grow the stablecoin network.
What do you mention these 16 different protocols? I mean, when you look at five years down the line,
do you think they'll be consolidation or it's a way for circle to hedge its bets if you want?
Or do you believe actually this is just going to continue to grow as the web tree ecosystem grows?
So my background is in internet infrastructure software. So I got started building web programming
languages, virtual machines, application infrastructure and worked in a lot of different parts of the
stack of internet infrastructure. And my general view is that blockchains are a new form of
distributed internet operating system. And effectively there is a lot of competition in those
operating systems, trying to attract developers and applications and the like. But I think increasingly
you're seeing the layering model as something that is relevant. And as we all know, the trade-offs
in terms of performance, security, privacy, other things, they're not perfect trade-offs.
I mean, there are people who I think believe that they can meet the scale needs of every
application, every user on a single layer. I think the layered model is going to continue
to grow. I think you'll see more and more. I think take, for example, if you're a giant consumer
scale company in India and you want to use digital tokens as a mechanism for your end users and
you're going to be minting and managing the lifecycle of these digital tokens and you
ultimately need those to be interoperable and portable with the global internet, you're very
likely going to do what people might call an app chain or a layer three. You're going to create
your own kind of compute space, your own store of data and memory, and you're going to kind of
hive it off. Just like in Amazon, we have virtual private clouds. Like everyone doesn't stick all
their stuff in one cloud. You have VPCs and you want to be able to hive off your own data,
your own compute, your own network perimeter, etc. There's going to be these kinds of scaling
models as well. And so there's a lot of really good competition in that infrastructure area.
But on this point, you mentioned India right now, again, five years down the line,
do you believe the majority of the activity you'll see on this kind of stuff will be in emerging
markets? I mean, if you look at today, obviously, we have a problem with remittances, we have a
problem when it comes to cross border transactions, but when it comes to within a country, most
transfers are working fine. On what you just mentioned on the stack, for example, do you believe
there'll be a faster acceleration adoption in EM emerging markets compared to the developed world?
So I guess my view is that we're really just in the early stages of the development of the
internet financial system. And we're talking about today, it's a tiny, tiny fraction of
the current scale of the global financial system. But the internet financial system,
I believe, ultimately will increase global economic output. We should see an acceleration
in economic output in the world because of the internet financial system and what it allows for.
So when you think about the market today, the market for existing forms of electronic money,
just fiat electronic money, it's about $100 trillion. And so clearly, just stablecoins themselves
have significant room to grow. But then the intermediation that goes on that's involved in
actual economic outputs of credit intermediation, time value of money, intermediation. I think
more and more of that will move into this on chain world as well. But I don't think the right
question is necessarily, is it emerging markets versus developed markets? The internet is awesome
in every country in the world. Like internet communications platforms are awesome
in every country in the world. The web is awesome in every country in the world. Meaning,
these general purpose infrastructures achieve scale and they deliver 10x or 100x better utility
than their predecessors. Like there's a time when, oh yeah, I could make a free long distance
telephone call in the United States. Well, why would I need a voice over IP or whatever? Is that
the point is that a model of money where the marginal cost of transacting goes to zero and
where money itself becomes a programmable composable form of data and object on the internet unlocks
utility in a way that's never existed before. And that's going to be hugely valuable in the
biggest capital markets in the world. It's going to be hugely valuable for the biggest corporations
in the world in developed markets. And it's going to be hugely valuable in international markets.
That's not to say that there aren't going to be use cases that achieve scale first in certain
places. So yes, we are seeing dramatic amounts of activity happening in cross border applications
of stablecoins today. That's like a very significant growth driver. But I think when you step back
and you think about the building blocks of the internet financial system and what that represents
to me, that's global scale and we'll touch every major market. But on this point Jeremy,
so we talk about the internet financial system, right? If we look today at the global crypto,
let's say the stablecoin ecosystem, right? What do you think that people want the regulated
USD stablecoin to use? For example, if we look right now, Tether obviously is the biggest
by market cap, right? In this internet of like the new financial system that's being developed,
what do you think people are looking for? Well, I think, you know, I mean, look, in an early stage
market which is sort of dominated by like offshore unregulated exchanges and it's mostly about
speculating on different things. That's one thing. The internet financial system is clearly about
actual economic activity. So if we want this to be useful, it has to be about actual economic
activity. And that means about people who are investing, saving, businesses that are needing
credit, that are building things that are hiring people, actually producing goods and services.
That's the real economy. So if we want the internet financial system to be used in the real economy,
not just for speculating on memes, like we have to have, you know, digital currency,
fiat stablecoins that are treated as real money that are cash equivalent so that if you're a
financial institution, you can take this and you can hold it as collateral. If you're, and
settlement, if you're a corporation, you know what this is. You're accounting firm. You're formerly
from a large big four, you know, universe. So an accounting firm can say this is a cash equivalent
instrument. I can treat it this way. I can report it this way. The entirety of this, we have to have
legally defined forms of stablecoins. And that's what's happening around the world, by the way,
which is great. Once you have these defined as like a new form of legal electronic money instrument,
then actually this can take hold at scale for real economic activity. And so that's really key.
We have to have that. If we don't have that, we're not, this is not going to take hold
as the basis of the internet financial system. And, you know, so that's a really, really key piece.
And do you believe the US dollar, like USDC or let's say, right now we look at the global
stablecoin ecosystem, US dollar, it's all US dollar denominated for a vast, vast majority of it,
right? It's very interesting because as you mentioned, you're going to different countries,
you know, if you're your central banker of an emerging country, your biggest, one of the risks
you have in a way is that the economy comes dollarized. If you're doing a bad job, which is in a way,
people have the option to switch the dollars or other currencies when, and we're seeing this from
anywhere from Nigeria to Turkey to Argentina and so on and so forth, right? How do you balance that
from your perspective when you're going these different markets saying, hey, we have a solution,
right? Now it's a US dollar based one and versus the country's own central bank from a policy
making where they want to have their own currency and control it because this could accelerate the
dollarization by the stablecoin usage. Well, you know, the internet has created these extraordinarily
powerful utilities that exist just using software that anyone who has a device can connect to
and people around the world have sort of said, hey, I like this, you know, WhatsApp or whatever
example you want to use, the ability to freely publish information to any person anywhere,
like there's sort of these super scale things that the internet has produced that in most societies
people really desire and then it's hard for the governments to put the genie back in the bottle
on those. Now, money, everyone's money is different and so on. We have a challenge, right? Part of
the challenge is that the vast majority of governments in the world are kind of bankrupt,
right? That meaning they're in debt, they're massively in debt, they're trying to monetize
that debt. We have huge issues with fiscal discipline, you know, it's a strong, you know,
it's a strong reason why non sovereign, you know, digital commodity money like Bitcoin is so
attractive is in the face of that. But it does, you know, the combination of sort of internet scale
financial utility based on things like digital dollars or digital euros and, you know, effectively
like this very, very high utility value that will come from those combined with the fiscal and
monetary challenges that face many, many countries. I do think that there's something brewing there,
it's going to be complicated and it's not clear exactly how that will get resolved but I, you know,
I have, you know, I do believe that individuals and firms will be able to vote with their sort
of software products, what economic system they want to participate in and it's going to involve,
you know, it's going to be a complex issue for a lot of jurisdictions.
Well, you can argue it's happening right now with many countries. I mean, look at Turkey,
where basically it's run on stablecoins now for big chunks of the economy. One thing as well,
on this point, which I think is interesting, like you guys have done a pretty good job
and actually on the DeFi space, for example, I see so many DeFi protocols now where the USDC plays
a pretty interesting role as well. When you look at the future of the stablecoin ecosystem,
we've had obviously some incidents last year with USD. Now there's an interesting thing with
ETINA and other projects going on. How do you find the future of stablecoin issuers? You believe in
5, 10, 15 years in this new model that we go in, it'll be centralized companies will be running it,
or it'll be more the next algorithmic stablecoin of this, or a version of ETINA that you'll see in
the future. Yeah, I guess I think if we're talking about sort of what's going to be used for real
economic activity that is going to be used by households and firms and financial institutions,
you're going to need to have legal forms of digital currency money, and those are going to be
regulated issuers, and those are going to be fully reserved. So you're going to have a full
reserve financial system, not a fractional reserve financial system, and you're going to have strong
supervision around those, and I think that those are going to achieve fairly large scale. Those will
grow into the trillions of dollars in circulation. Now that doesn't mean that there aren't going to be
other experiments in stable value tokens. There are obviously, there are, I mean, look, synthetic
derivatives that attempt to achieve a peg that provide some underlying basket of risk management
and yield, that's a separate thing. So synthetic securities and derivatives that are designed to
generate and pay yield, those are other types of financial products. So those types of financial
products will get regulated differently. They will not be regulated as payment systems. General
society will not depend on those as payment systems. Corporations, financial institutions will not hold
those on their balance sheets as collateral, but people who are trading, investing, seeking yield,
who are risk managing, are very likely going to purchase securities and derivatives that
manage their risk and their yield. So securities and derivatives play a huge role,
and I think that synthetic dollars that are securities and derivatives are going to continue
to grow. How those are regulated as an open question, right? I mean, I think we're seeing
enforcement around these historically. So I think how do you register these? How do you regulate
these? How do people access those? Let's call it regulated in a way. Well, yes. I think the whole
code is speech isn't going to work for everything. It doesn't work for AI. We're going to regulate
what AI's get produced. So I think it's more complicated than that. Jeremy, we have 60 seconds
left. My bell is here. I'm going to ask you quick questions. I need one or two word answers,
and when you kick it off from there, you ready? Sure. What is the biggest risk we're facing as a
crypto ecosystem for the next three years? One more time. What is the biggest risk we're facing as
a crypto ecosystem for the next three years? The biggest risk that we're facing for the next two
years is catastrophic failures continue with problematic companies and projects in crypto.
If you could go back to school today, what is the one course you would study that you wish you
had studied before? Synthetic biology. Interesting. What is the best advice you've ever received?
If you're stressed, take three deep breaths. If you could hold one crypto asset for the next 10
years, not USDC, what would you hold? I don't like those questions.
If you could go back in time, any time in history, what time would you want to go back?
That's a great question. I think I'd like to go back to the enlightenment.
The last question, Jeremy, to finish it off. A typical question, if you could have lunch or
dinner with one person dead or alive, lunch or dinner one person dead or alive, who would you
have lunch or dinner with? Probably an ancient relative of mine that I can't name right now.
Ladies and gentlemen, Jeremy Lares, CEO of Circle, thank you, Jeremy. Thank you.